太空堡垒卡拉狄加 【 前情提要 】
TYROL: Previously on Battlestar Galactica.
作为殖民地公民
I demand my rights as a Colonial citizen
我有权要求法律代表出庭 以及完整的法定诉讼程序
to legal representation and full due process.
是吗?
Do you?
那下一步怎么办?
So what happens next?
让他得到公正审判
We give him his trial.
家父曾是一名牧师 家母曾是一名先知
My father was a priest. My mother was an oracle.
我从18岁就在太空堡垒上服役
I've served a Battlestar since I was 18 years old.
当你们选我作工会主席的时候 我保证过会让大家有活干
When you elected me union president, I promised I would keep us working.
你们自己必须亲自爬在齿轮  杠杆...
You must throw your body on the gears and on the levers
机器上来阻止它们运转
and on the machine itself and make it stop!
罢工  罢工  罢工
ALL: Strike! Strike! Strike! Strike!
你还在装作我们的生活从未改变
You're pretending like nothing's changed,
和在新卡布里卡之前一样吗?
that our lives are exactly like they were before we went to New Caprica.
可的确已经不同了
But it is different.
恩  我们只是一时的困境罢了
Yeah, I was just going through a little rough patch.
如果是一世呢?
What if rough patches are all we have left?
菲戈斯基  波吕克斯 桑切斯
TYROL: Figurski, Pollux, Sanchez,
你们今晚修理所有轻便引擎 所以推掉所有夜生活吧
you're gonna be rehabbing mule engines tonight so don't make after-dinner plans.
把系统下线检测开关设为软件控制
Set and hold SOL check rigged to SEC.
我们不是让道格维尔的平民来替我们进行轻便引擎的维修么
I thought we were subbing out mule maintenance to the civvies in Dogsville?
对  可那里的技工不够
Yeah, we don't got enough mechanics down there.
检查流量
Check flow rate.
流量稳定在2-9-0
POLLUX: Flow rate steady at 290.
什么时候能有休息时间啊  轮机长?
Hey, when are we getting some rack around here, Chief?
我已经连续两周站两班了
I'm standing double watches the last two weeks.
我知道  我知道
I know, I know.
还有我的耳朵里还一直嗡嗡响
Plus, I still got the ringing in my ears.
耳朵里嗡嗡响!
MAN:The ringing in the ears!
对不起 我听不到你说什么 我耳朵里嗡嗡响 你说什么?
TYROL: I'm sorry, I can't hear you. I've got ringing. What's that?
伙计们 有意思
POLLUX: Real funny, guys.
燃料指示器坏了
Hey, fuse indicators are out.
机翼油箱开关设为"满油"  关机      好  停止加油
Set the wing tank switch to fuel. Power off. All right, tank off.
关闭燃料站
That's it. Kill the fueling stations.
拔出输油管   中尉  油已加满 可以起飞了
Pull the hose. Lt., you're tanked up and ready to roll.
收到  轮机长 准备起飞
Roger that, Chief. Ready to roll.
洗好的衣服到了 菲戈斯基 波吕克斯 莱夫
Laundry call, Figurski, Pollux, Redford.
快拿走你们的破烂 免得我塞到搅拌机里
Grab your crap before I chuck it in the cycler.
把内衣叠成我喜欢的样式了吗?
Fold my undies the way I like?
滚   嘴好刁哇
Frak off. Oh, nice mouth.
你说他们就让军官这样说话吗?
You think they let officers talk like that?
拿勋章的时候  可要把你的态度改一下
You're gonna have to change your ways when you get them wings.
拿不到勋章了
I'm not getting wings.
他们拒绝了我的飞行训练申请
They rejected my application for flight training.
但你在笔试中却拿了第一  面试不错吧?
I thought you aced the written exam. Interview went well?
恩  结果是我处于重要位置 我的离开将导致
Yeah, well, it turns out I'm in a critical position and my leaving would cause
严重任务退步
severe mission degradation.
真逊   "重要位置"个屁
That sucks. Critical position, my ass.
他们只是不愿意让乡巴佬坐进驾驶员的预备室
They just don't want knuckle-draggers stinking up the pilot ready room.
好了  够了 都闭嘴吧
All right, that's enough. Lock it up! That's enough.
空军队长告诉我  你从飞行训练落榜了
Look, the CAG told me you got bounced from flight training.
我很遗憾  这事不好受
I'm sorry about that. It sucks.
实话说 我们需要你  你是我们最好的航空设备技工
The truth is we need you down here, you're the best avionics specialist we got.
她还知道怎么来叠 老爷们的内衣
And she knows how to fold a man's undies.
嗨 哇 哇 你他妈…
Hey! Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa! You frak...
嗨 拜托 够了
Hey, come on! Hey, whoa! That's enough!
够了  别打了 你疯了?   我废了你
Enough! Get off! What, are you crazy? I'll take you apart!
少说两句  菲戈斯基
Hey! Shut up, Figurski!
看我不收拾你  快回去工作
I'll pop you in the mouth myself. Now get back to work.
过来  过来
Come here! Come here!
松手 听我说
Hey, hey, hey. Listen to me.
你在这里的工作和坐在驾驶舱里同等重要
Look, you do important work down here, just as important as sitting in a cockpit.
谢谢  轮机长
Thanks, Chief.
我要去派送一些重要的洗好的衣物了
I'm gonna deliver some more important laundry.
猛禽机升空了 读数正常
Raptor away. Readings nominal.
看来一切都不错  设置航线 飞向2-9-6-5-
Everything looks good. Setting course heading 2965...
怎么他妈回事?
What the frak?
熄火了  RCS推进器卡住了 (译注:RCS=反推力控制系统)
It's a flameout! RCS thrusters jammed!
重启 无效
Restart! No go!
卡拉狄加  我是斯卡司 二号引擎推进器完全堵塞
Galactica, Skulls. We have an engine thruster stuck in full position!
一号引擎无法启动
Engine one won't start!
二号引擎着火  快爆炸了 到这里来
There's a fire in engine two! It's gonna blow! Get your ass up here!
弹射  弹射  弹射
Eject! Eject! Eject!
我们走运  一打人受伤  无人遇难
You got off lucky. A dozen injuries. No fatalities.
谢谢
Thank you.
你应该检查一下托莉的肩膀
You should've seen Tory's shoulder.
我都得帮科特尔医生把它复原
I had to help Cottle put it back into alignment.
我一直很忙  几乎没机会到船的这端走走
You know, I am so busy, I hardly ever make it down to this end of the ship.
在舱壁修好前
And now I'm gonna be living here for God knows how long
我还要一直住这里
until they repair the bulkheads.
如果这里的房间太挤 我的另一张床永远欢迎你
If the quarters become cramped, you're always welcome in one of my beds.
一种说话方式而已
In a manner of speaking.
查清猛禽号出什么事了吗?
Do you have any better idea what happened to your Raptor?
还在调查情况
We're still investigating the situation.
不过看来是泰里恩受到了严重的杂质污染
But it seems that the tylium was seriously contaminated with impurities.
很可能是精炼过程中出现的问题
Most likely, it's a problem with the refining process.
那里到底怎么回事?
What the hell's going on there?
精炼船曾是舰队里最可靠的船只
The refinery used to be the most reliable ship in the fleet.
而现在我每天都能收到那边工头发来一堆的信息
Now every day I start with a stack of messages from that chief.
他叫什么名字?  吉诺・范纳
What is his name? Zeno Fenner.
范纳?    抱怨工作条件和交货时间
Fenner, complaining about working conditions and deliveries,
还有备件和补助  你能相信么
and spare parts and compensation, if you can believe that.
我们在逃命 这家伙却想着加班奖金
We're on the run for our lives and the guy wants to talk about overtime bonuses.
我们对范纳以及他的生产问题已经够宽容了
We've been more than patient with Fenner and his production problems.
给了他两周时间 让他重新投入工作
Two weeks of sitting here, waiting for him to get his act together.
我不知道你怎么想的 但我准备好去找地球了
I don't know about you, but I'm ready to get back on the road to finding Earth.
我看到的是希望的曙光吗?
Is that a hint of hope I hear?
怀疑主义者最后还是决定去寻找地球了?
Is the skeptic suddenly decided that we're on the road to Earth, after all?
我怀疑过吗?
Have I ever doubted it?
我手下的人六个月以来连续工作18个小时才换班
I've got people working 18 hour shifts for the past six months.
你们说一个人这样下去能坚持多久?
How long do you think a man can keep that up?
如果赛昂人出现了 我们的燃料足够让全舰队跳跃一次么?
If the Cylons show up, we have enough fuel to jump the entire fleet, what, once?
也许两次
Maybe twice?
这留给我可选择的空间太小了
That's a margin that's much too narrow for me.
对于你和你的手下呢?
How about for you and your men?
你有异议 自己想办法解决
You have a problem. Fix it.
继续生产燃料 其他事我们稍后再谈 我保证
Just get the gas flowing. And then we'll talk, I promise you that.
"再谈"?  总是稍后
Then we'll talk. It's always later.
有意思的是燃料生产了
You know, it's funny that when the gas flows,
我的电话却没回音
my phone calls don't get returned.
可一旦燃料供给中出现了小差错
But the minute there's a glitch in the fuel supply, I've got face time with
我就能和总统 上将见面了
the President and the Admiral.
嗯
Hmm...
也许我们还应该再有些小差错
Maybe we should just start having more glitches.
这算是威胁么?
Is that a threat?
正如那本书中所写到的一样...
It's like the book says.
"听取民声就不会惧怕民众"
"If you hear the people, you'll never have to fear the people. "
你是说"那本书"吗?
Did you say the book?
嗯
Mmm-hmm.
守卫 以在战时勒索及干扰重要服务…
Guards, arrest him for extortion and interrupting vital services
拘捕他
during a time of war.
来吧 把他带走  就这样  去吧 把他带出去
Go ahead, take him away. That's it. Go. Out of here. Gone.
跟我来  先生
Come with me, sir.
这又是哪一出戏?
What the hell was that?
他在引用波塔尔书中的原话
He was quoting from Baltar's book.
他的律师从禁闭室里带出的那些乱七八糟的东西?
The ramblings that his lawyer smuggled out of the brig?
他让人重印后在舰队里分发
He's having it reprinted and passed out among the Fleet
还把书名定为《我的成与败》 盖尤斯・波塔尔著
and he's calling it My Triumphs, My Mistakes, by Gaius Baltar.
我在考虑来一场老套的焚书运动
I am thinking of having a good old-fashioned book-burning.
肉糕好吃吗? 开始喜欢吃肉糕了
Ooh, algae meatloaf, starting to be a favorite.
那不是给你吃的 还记得我们的谈话吗?
It's not for you. Remember our little talk?
今天是我的"作弊日" (译注:节食过程中  一周内唯一可以大吃大喝的日子)
Oh, but today's my cheat day.
前三天都是你的"作弊日"
The last three days have been your cheat day.
是吗?
Really?
你昨天移动更灵活的
You were moving better yesterday.
屈身运动就这点用处?
Is that how the bends are supposed to work?
我只是替希里克斯难过 所以有点紧张
I'm just upset about Seelix, so I'm tensing up.
他们早就该告诉她舰队里的首要任务是什么
They should've just told her right off the bat what the fleet priorities are.
应该告诉她 比起驾驶员来
Should've said that they needed knuckle-draggers
他们更需要工人
more than they need pilots.
这不是"舰队首要任务"的问题
It isn't about fleet priorities.
我们不是统治阶级 所以只能干脏活
We're not part of the ruling class, so we're stuck doing the dirty work.
"统治阶级"  这词你从哪听到的?
The ruling class? Where'd you get that?
我读的书上 波塔尔写的书
Something I read, by Baltar.
这些破书还在舰队里传开了
Those frakking rags making their way around the fleet?
没想到还会有人去看那家伙写的东西
I can't believe that anybody's reading anything written by that guy.
我原本也是那么想的 可是…
That's what I thought too, but...
你是否想过为何所有驾驶员和军官都来自富有的殖民地?
You ever wonder why all the pilots and the officers come from the rich Colonies,
像是卡布里卡  沃钢 或是特诺朗
like Caprica, and Virgon, Tauron?
而所有工人都来自贫穷的殖民地
Well, all the knuckle-draggers come from the poor Colonies,
像是爱诺朗  撒纪特恩  还有杰米纳
like Aerelon and Sagitarron and Gemenon.
甲板手扯蛋而已
Yeah, that's just trash talk on the deck.
是吗?  在舰队里挑出一个来自贫穷殖民地的军官
Really? Name one officer on the Fleet that comes from a poor Colony.
杜亚拉  杜亚拉中尉来自撒纪特恩
Dualla, Lieutenant Dualla's from Sagitarron.
这就是例子  她怎么升职的?
Case in point. How did she get promoted?
她嫁给了一位来自卡布里卡的军官
She married an officer from Caprica.
我是蒂罗尔
Tyrol.
轮机长 燃料精炼厂的工头已经被逮捕了
ADAMA: Chief, the foreman at the fuel refinery's just been arrested.
吉诺・范纳?   你认识他?
Zeno Fenner? Do you know him?
吉诺出了什么事吗?
Did something happen to Zeno?
被捕了   是的 长官   在新卡布里卡上的时候 他曾是工会中的一员
Arrested. Yes, sir. He was in the union on New Caprica.
他看起来人不错  犯了什么事?
He seemed like a good guy. What'd he do?
他惹总统生气了
He pissed off the President.
不过当前更大的问题是精炼厂的生产任务
But the bigger problem right now is the refining operation.
必须有人去那里 让燃料船投入工作
I need someone to go over there and get that fuel ship moving again.
组成一支小组  带上装备一小时内到达机库
Pick a team, get your gear and be on the hangar deck in an hour.
是  长官
Yes, sir.
我不明白 吉诺出了什么事?
I don't understand. What happened to Zeno?
把总统惹了
He pissed off the President.
现在因为这事都会被捕了?
You mean, you can get arrested for that now?
我看上将是在开玩笑
I think the Admiral was kidding.
是啊
Yeah.
你想起过工会吗?
You ever think about the union?
当然 但那已经一去不复返了
Sure, but that's gone now.
新卡布里卡已经一去不复返了 但工会里所有的人还在这里
New Caprica's gone, but all the people in the union are still here.
唯一的差别就是 现在没人为他们出头
The only difference is now they don't have anyone to stand up for them.
我得走了
I gotta go.
希望你们能尽兴
I do hope you're enjoying yourselves.
打扰了我的休息 弄脏了我的食物还不够
It's not enough that you have to interrupt my sleep and put filth in my food.
现在还来毁坏我的用品 你们真是无理取闹
Now you have to destroy my stuff as well. You're pathetic!
你们完全根本--
You're utterly and totally...
你好啊  博士
Hello, Doctor.
识相点
Why don't you do yourself a favor?
把书页交出来  就此罢手吧
Hand over the pages and stop all this nonsense.
我不知道你是什么意思
I don't know what you're talking about.
把他转过来
Turn him around.
你写的书的书页 《我的成与败》盖尤斯・波塔尔所著
The pages to your book, My Triumphs, My Mistakes by Gaius Baltar.
你读过了?
So, you've read it.
民众读了这本书 你感到惭愧了
The people are reading it and now you're sorry.
我们知道你的律师把书页悄悄携带出去已有几周时间了
We've known that your lawyer was smuggling the pages out of here for weeks.
所以全被我们截获了 恐怕只有我拜读了大作
So, we intercepted them and I'm afraid I'm the only one who's read the book,
所以我很想知道它的结局
and I am dying to see how it ends.
你现在真的把自己当作平民出身的人?
Really, what were you thinking now, casting yourself as a man of the people,
一个农民的儿子?  一个革命份子?
the son of a farmer, a revolutionary?
可得了吧
Oh, please.
说出来你也许会惊讶 总统阁下
It may come as some surprise to you, Madam President,
但我希望以普通人的身份来打动法庭
but I wish to strike a chord with the common man.
把书页交出来  不然我就让这些守卫搜你的身
Hand over those pages or I'll have these guards search you.
你自己选择
Make a choice.
各位  继续
Gentlemen, proceed.
别向她屈服  盖尤斯
Don't bend to her, Gaius.
让她知道  她无法让你动摇
Show her that she can't break you.
保持你的尊严
Keep your dignity.
可能你会考虑一下在封底写个简评
Perhaps you'd consider writing a blurb for the back cover.
谢谢  博士
Thank you, Doctor.
关上牢门
GUARD: Close cell.
没事  盖尤斯  一切都会没事的
It's all right, Gaius. Everything will be okay.
蒂罗尔
Tyrol!
凯伯 嗨
Cabott! Hey.
还好吗
How you doing?
很高兴见到你
Good to see you.
抱歉      没关系 难免的事
Sorry. Never mind. It's inevitable.
哥们  我不得不说...
Listen, I gotta tell ya,
知道他们要派你来的时候  我们就觉得好多了
we all started feeling a lot better when we heard they were sending you.
是吗?      那是
Oh, yeah? You bet.
我一直在说你的好话
I've been talking you up,
说新卡布里卡上工会...
telling everybody how the union on New Caprica
是如何为小人物出头的
really stood up for the little guy.
恩
Yeah, well...
你看到的就是整个舰队的泰里恩了
You're looking at the Fleet's entire fuel supply of tylium.
我们还能跳跃多少次?
How many jumps you think we got?
能跳出这个星系就算走运了
We'll be lucky if we get out of the system.
你最好带我四处看一下 看一下我们目前的情况
Well, you'd better give us the nickel tour, see where we stand.
大场面
This is a big operation.
等这地方全部运转起来后 你再看看这里
Yeah, well, you should see this place when it's up and running.
比炸弹还响 就比它安全一些
Loud as an A-bomb and just about as safe.
我们真的需要一些休息时间 看看周围
Listen, we really need this downtime. I mean, look around.
下次机器出现故障  可能就不只废了一架猛禽机了
Next time some machine fraks up, it might not just take out a Raptor.
这艘船真是一颗随时可能爆炸的炸弹
This ship really is a big bomb just waiting to go up.
我知道有风险  但我必须要让这里开始工作
Yeah, look, I understand the risk, but I need to see it working,
所以把你的人都叫上  开始工作吧
so pull your guys off, and let's fire it up.
这么做没用
It ain't gonna work.
你在这里上班?
You work here?
这位是麦洛 我最好的润滑手
This is Milo. He's the best grease jockey I got.
麦洛是吧?  告诉我   麦洛  为什么行不通?
Milo, huh? Hey, Milo, so why is it not gonna work?
有什么事没告诉我?  说吧
Something you guys aren't telling me? Come on.
好吧 看来我得自己看看了
Okay. I guess I'm just gonna have to have a look for myself.
那是卸压阀么?
Is that pressure relief?
密封环不见了?
The seals are missing.
都不见了
They all are.
没有压力密封环  机器运转不了
Without pressure seals, the machinery won't run.
到哪去了?
Well, where are they?
看来是丢了
Guess they got lost, huh?
伙计们  你们不能拿这开玩笑
Guys, you can't be frakking around with this stuff.
上将不会容忍这种行为   让上将见鬼去吧
The Admiral won't stand for it. The Admiral can kiss my ass.
嗨 嗨!
Hey, hey!
拜托  轮机长 你也知道这是为什么
Come on, Chief, you know what this is about.
我想工作环境如果有所改善
I guess when working conditions improve
再把吉诺放出来的话  我们就能找到那些密封环了
and they let Zeno out of jail, we'll be able to find those seals.
在此之前 这艘船
Until then, it looks like this ship
不会炼出一粒泰里恩
isn't going to be refining another drop of tylium.
就是说这支舰队哪都去不了
And that means this Fleet isn't going anywhere.
我已经搜遍了整艘船  还是没有找到密封环
I've executed a search of the ship, but the seals have not turned up.
你也知道  这是蓄意破坏
You know that this is sabotage.
我要把他们关起来
I'm inclined to have them locked up.
长官  求你  他们可以安装一些东西来暗害我
Sir, please, they could've rigged something to have me injured.
他们可以故意污染燃料
They could have contaminated the fuel on purpose
让我们所有的船爆炸
and left all of our ships dead in the air.
我的天
Good Gods.
而他们所做的就是为了争取一些时间
All they did do was buy themselves some time.
机器确实需要大修
The machinery does need overhauling.
质量控制办事不力是有原因的
There's a reason that the quality control is failing.
你要知道那艘船上大部分工人...
Do you realize that most of the workers on that ship
自从殖民地遇袭后 一天也没休息过
have not had a day off since the original attack on the Colonies?
像是在做苦役一样
It's like slave labor.
别乱说了
Don't be absurd.
那艘船上的人被困在了那里
The men and women aboard that ship are stuck there.
无法脱身  无法调职
They can't leave, they can't transfer.
无法掌握自己的命运
They have no control over their lives.
并且工作繁重 这我们知道
And the work is hard, we know that.
他们是以为自己在海藻加工厂...
Do they think they're having a picnic on the algae processing plant
或是军火库  废物处理厂吃野餐吗?
or munitions or waste processing?
舰队里的飞船都载满了在恶劣环境下工作的人
The fleet is filled with ships with people working under horrific conditions
并没有人在安心享乐
and nobody's having a good time.
我认为  如果我们能至少放了吉诺
Well, I think that if we at least release Zeno and start talking to them
然后和他们谈一些有关改善工作与居住环境的问题
about improving working conditions and living conditions,
抗议就会停止 他们就会归还压力密封环
that the protest will go away, they'll return the pressure seals
我们也就能控制燃料污染问题
and we'll get the fuel contamination problem under control.
这种勒索的抗议方法是不可接受的
Extortion is not an acceptable method of protest.
带头人叫什么名字?
What are the names of the leaders?
只有凯伯   我会下达对他的逮捕令
Just Cabott. I will issue a warrant for his arrest.
把他关禁闭  震慑一下他
Put him in the brig, let him sweat it out.
上将  总统阁下  他们只是想..
Admiral, Madam President, they're just trying to...
轮机长  打住  话说完了
Chief, uh-uh. We're done.
我要去看一下凯伯和吉诺
I'm gonna go check on Cabott and Zeno.
轮机长
Chief?
嗨 嗨
Hey. Hey.
你得把他弄出去
You gotta get him out of here.
他的手怎么了?
What the hell happened to his hands?
他半夜起来抓墙
I wake up in the middle of the night, he's scratching the walls.
抓个没完 直到手指出血
He just keeps scratching them until his fingers are bleeding.
我不说  我不在乎
I won't say, it don't matter...
他在新卡布里卡上的时候 就被赛昂人拘留过 记得吗?
He was in Cylon detention on New Caprica, you remember?
他出来以后就怪里怪气的 这么做对他有害无益
He came out all squirrelly, and this is not helping.
拜托 你得把他弄出去
Come on, you've got to get him out of here.
我不会说的
I won't say...
密封环在哪里?
Where are the seals?
你个狗杂种 说吧
You son of a bitch. Come on!
拜托  加伦 你得把他弄出去
Come on, Galen! You've got to get him out of here!
凯伯!      不  我不说
Cabott? I won't say. No, I won't...
凯伯  看着我
Cabott, look at me.
凯伯  听我说 密封环在哪里?
Cabott, listen to me. Where are the seals?
我不说  我不在乎 不在乎
I won't say. It doesn't matter. It doesn't matter.
凯伯  我能救你出来  密封环在哪里?
Cabott, I can get you out of here. Where are the seals?
告诉我在哪里?      密封环在哪里?
Tell me where the seals are. I won't say. It doesn't matter...
老天啊  救他出去      我不在乎 我不在乎
For Gods sakes, get him out of here! It doesn't matter! It doesn't matter!
密封环在哪里?  在哪里?
Where are the seals? Where are they?
我不在乎  我不在乎       密封环在哪里?
It doesn't matter. It doesn't matter! Where are the seals?
我不在乎  我不在乎       在哪里?
It doesn't matter! It doesn't matter! Where are they?
通风口
The air vent!
行了吧?  在船尾中间的通风口里
All right? They're in the center stern air vent!
告诉总统放了他们
Tell the President to release them.
好 这是最后一个
All right, that's the last one.
点火 回去工作
Let's fire this up, get back to work.
是  长官      一切听从你的吩咐  老大
Yes, sir. Whatever you say, boss.
嗨 嗨    可以让我来开闸吗?
Hey, hey, hey, hey. Can I throw the switch?
你多大?      12岁
How old are you? Twelve.
快12岁了
Almost.
可所有的机器  我都会操作
But I can run every machine we got.
唯一没做过的事  就是开闸
Only thing I haven't done is turn the whole thing on.
归你了
It's all yours.
那下面全是一些孩子  总统阁下
TYROL: There are kids down there, Madam President.
舰队里的每艘船上都有小孩
There's children on every ship in the fleet.
这些孩子在精炼厂工作
These children work in the refinery.
他们只有12岁  15岁
They're 12, 15 years old.
自从有精炼厂的那一天开始 就有家庭住在那里
There have been families aboard the refinery ever since its beginning,
其他人则是在赛昂 袭击殖民地后被接上船的
and others were picked up after the Cylons attacked the Colonies.
在过去的两年中
Over the past two years,
家长一直在教授儿女如何操作机器
the parents have been teaching the children how to operate the machinery.
他们在把自己的技能传给下一代  这是很正常的事
They have been passing along their skills. It is perfectly normal.
这么做并不理想 我也知道
It is not ideal, I know that.
但这支舰队本身就没有什么理想之处
But there is nothing ideal about this Fleet.
您看出来这是怎么回事了么?
Do you see what's happening?
工作开始代代相传  总统阁下
Jobs are starting to be inherited, Madam President.
我们并不知道还要在这船上呆多久 如果是十年呢?
We don't know how long we're gonna be on these ships. What if it's 10 years?
就因为我是甲板手  我就非要把我的儿子训练成甲板手?
So, I train my son to be a deck hand because that's what I am?
就因为他只是这块料?
And that's all he can ever be?
这是我们想要的未来吗?
Is that the future we want?
你说得很对
That's a really good point.
托莉  制作一份名单  列出舰队里
Tory, I want you to make a list of everyone in the Fleet
所有适合从事精炼工作的人
who has a work history appropriate to the refinery.
工厂工人   技工  所有你能想到的工种
Factory workers, mechanics, whatever you think.
然后交给轮机长 你来主持公开抽签
Give it to the Chief and I want you to hold a public lottery.
我们从其他船上找人
And we will take people from other vessels
让他们与精炼厂的工人轮班
and we'll put them on shifts in the refinery.
怎么样  轮机长?
How's that, Chief?
谢谢您   谢谢你
Thank you. Thank you.
那些就是从道格维尔分配来的人?
TYROL: So that's our allotment from Dogsville.
在他们知道要去哪之前
We'll get these people on these ships and out of here
就把他们带上船  离开这里
before they know where they're going.
好了  各位  我们排两行      打扰一下  先生
All right, people! Let's form two lines! Excuse me, sir!
一排这边 一排那边…
One down here, one over here...
我不知道应该找谁谈这件事
Hi, I don't really know who I'm supposed to talk to about this,
可我想我不是你们要找的人
but I don't really think I'm what you guys are looking for.
我没有这项技能
I don't really have the skills.
你叫什么名字?  丹尼・努
What's your name? Danny Noon.
菲戈斯基?    努?
Figurski? Noon.
努 努 努 丹尼 这上面写着你是农民
Noon. Noon. Noon, Daniel. Says you're a farmer.
农民?  这正是我们要找的人
Farmer? Yeah, that's what we're looking for.
可以操作重型机器的人    不 可我不会
People to work with heavy machinery. No, but I don't.
不太会
Not really.
我为了攒钱上大学  一夏天都曾在一座农场打工
I worked on a farm for a summer because I was saving up to go to college.
专业是建筑学 接着就遭遇了赛昂人的袭击
Architecture, but then the Cylons attacked,
而我现在就成了农民  这怎么合理?
and now I'm a farmer? How is that fair?
从哪一点看是合理的?
How is that in any way fair?
失陪一下
Just give me a second.
如果为他开绿灯  其他人就会跟风而至
We make an exception for this guy, there's gonna be 15 more right behind him.
看看他  还是个孩子
Look at him, though. He's a kid.
好吧  把他带上船
Fine. Put him on the ship.
这只是暂时的  好吗?
Look, this is just a temporary thing, okay?
等一下  我不是农民
Hey, wait, hold on. I'm not a farmer!
这不是固定工作
Yeah, it's not permanent.
等一下 你能看一下我的档案吗?      好
No, wait, can you just check my record? Yeah.
请问 我该找谁谈这件事?
Excuse me. Who am I supposed to talk to about this?
我该找谁谈这件事?
Who am I supposed to talk to about this?
你怎么不明白 我不是农民
You don't understand! I'm not a farmer!
住手  我不是农民
Hey! Stop it! I'm not a farmer!
你来这里干什么?
What are you doing here?
你的书 是真实的还是虚构的?
Your book, fact or fiction?
你读过了?
So you read it?
这也就证明了总统是个十足的骗子
Well, that proves that the President is an accomplished liar.
她告诉我那本书还没上市 有什么感想?
She told me it hadn't gone out. So what do you make of it?
我看是一派胡言
I think that it's a pile of crap.
显然  我对两极分化社会所作的分析让你害怕了
Obviously, my analysis of a bifurcated society scares you.
不过在我书中所叙述的每件事恰恰都是事实
But everything in my book happens to be true.
是真的？ 你真的是一个从爱诺朗来的农村孩子？
Oh, it's true? It's true that you're a farm boy from Aerelon.
对  确实是这样
Yes, it is, as a matter of fact.
我确实生长在爱诺朗上
I was born and raised on a dairy outside the town
科菲波里沃镇外的一座牛奶厂
of Cuttlesbreath Wash on Aerelon.
我怎么就想象不出你在挤牛奶
Why do I have such a hard time picturing you
施肥时会是什么样呢?
milking cows and shoveling manure?
缺乏想象力
Lack of imagination.
不然就是你的小故事本身就是谎话
Or maybe that your little tale is manure.
我认识从爱诺朗来的人 你听起来和他们不一样
I've known people from Aerelon. You don't sound anything like them.
我听起来不像是从爱诺朗来的?      不像
I don't sound like I'm from Aerelon? No.
我把这句话当作是你对我的褒奖
Well, you know I take that as a particular compliment.
我不知道你有什么感觉  可我认为爱诺朗方言
I don't know about you, but I've always found the Aerelon dialect
向来都是对耳朵的一种折磨
to be particularly hard on the ears.
主要是那些
Something about the consonants
从喉咙后部发出的辅音
that scrape the back of the throat.
当然  我应该非常熟悉自己的口音
Of course, I should know an awful lot about my native tongue.
我曾连续用几小时来纠正它
I spent hours on end trying to overcome it.
你知道对于一个10岁的男孩来说
Do you have any idea how hard it is
要改变他的说话方式有多难?
for a 10-year-old boy to change the way he speaks?
要把他所学到的一切东西都忘掉
To unlearn everything he ever learned
这样有一天 有一天 可能会有一丁点希望
so that one day there might be the small hope
大家认为他可能不是来自爱诺朗的人
that he might be considered as not coming from Aerelon?
也许是从卡布里卡来的人
Maybe, I don't know, Caprica?
卡布里卡人 当一个卡布里卡人
Caprica? Oh, to be Caprican.
政治  文化  艺术 科学  学识的温床
The seat of politics, culture, art, science, learning.
而爱诺朗呢?  丑陋的土褐色星球
And what was Aerelon? Just a drab, ugly rock,
被判为是12殖民地的粮仓
condemned to be the food basket for the 12 worlds.
我们也受到像佣人  劳工  工人阶级一般的对待
And that's how we were treated, like servants, like laborers, like working class.
你倒是很符合标准  轮机长
You know, you would have fitted right in there, Chief.
很多人都喜欢手工劳动 到酒馆喝杯酒
Lots of men who liked to work with their hands and grab a pint down at the pub
找人打一架后来结束一天的辛劳
and finish off the evening with a good old-fashioned fight.
对了 我在过完18岁生日后 就离开了爱诺朗
Oh, yes, I left Aerelon after my 18 birthday.
抛下了我的家族 我的遗产 所有的一切
I turned my back on my family, on my heritage, all of them.
当然说也白说了 一切都毁于一旦了
Of course, it doesn't matter. They're all dead now.
你也清楚这里也没有那些东西吧?
You do realize that none of that exists here.
从技工嘴里说出的话
Coming from the mouth of a mechanic.
我们保留了民主
We've kept democracy.
我们有政府 有权利  有选举
We have government, we have rights, we have elections...
那你完全应该感到高兴才对  不是吗?
Well, then you should feel perfectly happy, shouldn't you?
非常舒适自在 回家吧 别烦我
Perfectly at ease. Go home! Leave me in peace!
这正是贵族阶级所期盼的
After all, that's what the aristocracy wants.
想要让工人阶级觉得自己受人爱戴
It wants the working class to feel looked after,
而他们其实吃的却是主人的残羹冷炙
while they scrabble around for scraps from the master's table.
书的结尾我提出了一个问题
There's a question I ask at the end of my book.
免得你再去看了
I'll save you the trouble of reading it.
你真的认为这支舰队
Do you honestly believe that the Fleet will ever be commanded
可以由不姓亚当玛的人来统治吗?
by somebody whose last name is not Adama?
就是这样  轮机长
There it is, Chief.
对贵族阶级是一套规矩
One set of rules for the aristocracy,
对我们是一套规矩
and one set of rules for the rest of us.
我们已经给那些经过抽签决定新来的工人分配了任务
FENNER: We've given assignments to all the new workers from the lottery.
看来你让他们马上投入了工作
Looks like you put 'em right to work.
恩  对  他们还好  虽然不太稳重 但是会好起来的
Yeah, yeah. They're okay. They're a little skittish, but they'll catch on.
我们上次的问题就出在这里
Right up here's where we had the problem last time.
多次出现齿轮滑动  温度变动
We got all kinds of gear slippage, temperature variations.
我们并不知道残渣没有被烧掉
We didn't know the dross wasn't getting burned off.
是你们的不合格燃料?
And that's the bad fuel?
对  现在开始流动了 生产线上还有六个地方
Yeah, it's running now, but we've got a half-dozen other places
可能会出现故障
down the line that could frak us.
怎么回事?
What's that?
好了  关闸
Whoa, that's it! Hit the switch!
不行  不行  卡住的时候不能关  整个系统都会失灵
No, no, no! Not when it's jammed! The whole system will seize up!
我们得找到卡住的地方 否则留在室内的矿石过热后
Gotta find it. Otherwise, the ore that's still in the chambers will superheat
会产生连锁反应  把我们都炸飞
and set off a chain reaction that will blow us all to hell!
快  我们一定要让传送带动起来
Hurry! We've got to get this going!
在这里  就是这里
Right here! This is it!
找到了?  恩
You got it? Yeah!
把它弄出来
Get it out of there.
我没法抓到它
I can't get my hands around it.
快  拉一下 我抓不住它
Come on, just give it a yank! I can't get my hand on it!
小心  小心
Careful! Careful!
这下面太窄了 我进不去
It's too small. I can't get under it.
那边的矿石都热了 你们得快点让这东西动起来
We've got some hot rocks up there! You've got to get this thing started fast!
拉一下  拉一下  我就是抓不住它
Give it a yank! Give it a yank! I just can't get my hand around it!
抓不住
I can't get my hand on it!
我来试试 我来试试
I can try! I can try!
我也许能进去
Get in there! I can probably fit.
来吧  丹尼   如果弄好了
Come on, Danny. Okay, if he clears it,
传送带会跳带 你要小心
the belt's gonna jump, so you gotta be careful.
从后面进去 抓到它
Way in the back. Got it.
小心  抓到了 抓到了
There you go, there you go. You got it. You got it.
好  小心点
You got it. Atta boy. Better... Be careful!
加油  丹尼 让它动起来
Come on, Danny, get a hold of it!
对  好样的 抓住它  拉住
That's it! Atta boy! Now, grab it! Pull it!
往你这边拉 用力拉
Pull it towards you! Pull hard!
用力拉 用力拉
Come on! Pull hard, Danny!
这就对了
Yes! All right!
好样的 丹尼 干得好
Good work, Danny. Good work.
好样的  快出来 快出来
Atta boy, Danny. Get out of there. Come on out, come on out.
急救员!  急救员!
Medic! Medic!
急救员快来!
Medic! Now!
放松  小兄弟  我们会照顾好你的
Take it easy, buddy. We got you. We're gonna work with you.
放松…    他重度…
Go ahead, take it easy... He's got multiple...
没事  小兄弟 你做得很好
FENNER: It's okay, buddy. You did a great job. A great job.
快进去
MAN: Get in there! Get in there!
好
SEELIX: Okay.
你会好的
You're gonna be okay.
还需要纱布   冷静   再拿些来
I need more gauze. Just calm down, that's it. Give me some more.
这地方停止作业了
This plant is off-line!
我们要罢工!
We're on strike!
需要什么吗  上尉?
You need something, Captain?
对 我他娘的是需要东西 需要我的蝮蛇机
Yeah, I frakking need something. I need my Viper.
抱歉  上尉  仅限于重要任务
Sorry, Captain. Vital missions only.
空中巡逻队已经出勤 我们做完工作了
CAP is already up. We did our job.
"重要任务"是什么意思?
What do you mean, vital missions only?
谁的命令?
Whose orders?
凯莉传达了蒂罗尔轮机长的命令
Cally relayed the orders from Chief Tyrol.
我们罢工了
We're on strike.
上将
Admiral.
你是否意识到你的甲板手们参与了停工活动?
Are you aware that your deck gang is participating in a work stoppage?
这叫做总罢工  长官  这是兵变
It's called a general strike, sir. It's a mutiny.
知道我们怎么处置叛徒么?
And do you know what we do with mutineers?
我们枪毙他们  轮机长
We shoot them, Chief.
我们这是在抛弃民众  上将
We're leaving people behind, Admiral.
民众被固定在他们的岗位 无法掌握自己的命运
People are locked into their jobs, they have no control over their lives.
没有权利
They have no say.
我们让他们听天由命 就像是我们把他们遗弃在了那个星球上
We're abandoning them to their fate. It's like we've marooned them on a planet.
问题不在这里
That is not the issue.
这艘战舰上的人不许违抗命令
The men and women on this ship are not allowed to disobey an order,
特别是为了支持什么狗屁劳资纠纷
especially in support of some kind of frakking labor dispute.
我们送出了空中巡逻队
We launched the CAP.
没人擅自离岗  我们并没让舰队面临危险
No one has abandoned their post. We're not putting anyone in danger.
这是兵变
This is mutiny.
到此为止
And it stops now.
上将 我只想和总统坐下来谈一些事
Admiral, all I want is a sit-down with the President.
我是上将
This is the Admiral.
逮捕凯莉・蒂罗尔
Arrest Cally Tyrol.
把她直接武装押送到右舷修理厂
Take her under armed guard directly to the starboard repair bay.
"修理厂"?  你要干什么?
The repair bay? What are you doing?
我要让她靠着舱壁 把她作为叛徒枪毙
I'm gonna put her up against the bulkhead and I'm gonna shoot her as a mutineer.
你是不是疯了?
Are you out of your frakking mind?
凯莉只是按我命令行事
Cally was just following my orders.
她是带头人  所以第一个人就是她
She's a ringleader, so she goes first.
接着就是其他的甲板手 菲戈斯基 希里克丝 波吕克斯…
Then the rest of your deck gang, Figurski, Seelix, Pollux...
你不会这么做的
You won't do this.
我们有一个儿子
We have a son.
给我听好
Understand me.
这艘战舰的生死存亡也许正依赖于那些接到命令
The very survival of this ship may depend on someone getting an order
但却不愿执行命令的人
that they don't want to do.
如果他们稍有迟疑
And if they hesitate,
如果他们有时把上级命令当作耳旁风
if they feel that orders are sometimes optional,
那这艘战舰就会灭亡
then this ship will perish,
你的儿子也会有此下场 全人类也会灭亡
and so will your son and the entire human race.
我确实不想这么做 轮机长
I don't want to do this, Chief.
但为了确保这艘战舰 这支舰队不会被摧毁
But I will put 10 Callys up against the wall
就算有十个凯莉在 我也会把她们送上刑场
to make sure that this ship and this fleet are not destroyed.
好吧
Fine.
我停止这次罢工
I'll call it off.
我是上将
This is the Admiral.
凯莉被拘留了么?
Do you have Cally in custody?
让她听电话  把门打开
Put her on. Open the door.
你还好吧?      不用担心我
You okay? CALLY: Don't worry about me.
我进过禁闭室
I've been in a brig before.
一切都很顺利
TYROL: Everything's okay.
停止罢工
Call off the strike.
他们让步了?
Did they cave?
恩
Yeah.
停止吧
Call it off.
我就知道   交给我吧
I knew it. I'll take care of it.
加伦  我为你自豪
Galen, I'm proud of you.
把电话给陆战队员吧
Give the phone to the Marine.
放了她
Release her.
你可以走了 轮机长
You can go now, Chief.
你不是还要和总统讨论一些事么
I thought you had something that you wanted to discuss with the President.
还要一杯吗?      不用了
Would you like another drink? I think I've had enough.
总统阁下
Madam President,
我发现入伍后士兵的兵种完全取决于他们的出生地在哪里
I've seen people drafted into service based purely on where they were born.
也取决于他们所拥有的技能
They've also been selected based on their skills.
而这正是由他们的出生地所决定的
Which is a result of where they were born.
卡布里卡人很可能是专业人员
Capricans are more likely to be professionals.
爱诺朗人很可能是农民
Aerelons are more likely to be farmers.
这就是残酷的现实
It's just a fact of life.
可以改变的现实
It's a fact I can't change.
那倒是真的 不过我认为我们可以公平竞争
True. But I think we can level the playing field.
舰队里 每天都有许多脏活累活
There are a lot of dirty jobs that need to be done every day in this fleet,
清洗  修理 简单维护 诸如此类的工作
cleaning, hauling, low-level maintenance, things like that.
我认为这类工作应该分配给...
These are the kind of jobs that I think should be allocated to people,
那些像您一样的人 恕我冒昧
well, people like yourself. No offense.
我不介意 继续说
None taken. Go ahead.
让殖民者一号上的一些人干些脏活
Let some of the people on Colonial One get their hands dirty for a change.
就这么定了 还有什么?
Done. What else?
在危险与高压环境下工作的人
People that are in dangerous and high stress jobs
需要轮换连续作业
need to be rotated out for R and R.
如果要这么做  我们就需要正式的培训计划
Now, in order to do that, we need a formal training program.
我们可以稍后再谈培训计划
We can talk about a training program later, but right now I need to focus
但当前我们的重点是保持现有的劳动力
on maintaining the work force that we have,
而这正是工会失职的地方
and this is gonna have to be an area where the union gives ground.
"工会"?
The union?
不好意思 你不是代表殖民地工人联盟
Oh, I'm sorry, I thought you were engaged in collective bargaining
进行集体谈判么
on behalf of the Colonial Workers' Alliance.
如果不是这样...    总统阁下
If that's not the case, then... Madam President,
那个工会已经在新卡布里卡上灭亡了
that union died on New Caprica.
轮机长 这支舰队里的工人
Chief, the workers in this fleet, they need someone
需要一位可以代表他们权益的人
to represent them and their interests.
如果这个社会确实正演变成...
And if this society is becoming truly polarized
平稳的政治阶层与被剥夺公民权的下层社会的两极分化
between an entrenched political class and a disenfranchised underclass,
那我们就命不久矣了
we are doomed.
用不着赛昂人来消灭我们 我们就会毁了我们自己
We won't need the Cylons to destroy us, we'll destroy ourselves.
到达地球的舰队根本就无法代表殖民社会
The fleet that arrives at Earth will not represent Colonial society at all.
我愿意用尽毕生精力来为实现那个殖民社会而奋斗
I am willing to fight for that society until my dying breath.
如果你也能这么做 那就再好不过了
I would love it if you would fight for that society as well.
嗯
Hmm.
我会的
I will.
我会的  总统阁下 我会这么做的
I will, Madam President. I will.
波吕克斯和赫歇耳 你们负责为4372号加燃料
TYROL: Pollux and Herschel, you are on fueling 4372.
蒂罗尔轮机长?
STARBUCK: Chief Tyrol.
上尉
Hey, Captain.
我的一名傻蛋今早没有…
Chief, one of my nuggets failed to show up
出席基础飞行训练课
for basic flight instruction this morning.
我很遗憾  上尉
Sorry to hear that, Captain.
也许你能告诉我 戴安娜・希里克丝在哪里?
So maybe you can tell me where the hell Diana Seelix is?
希里克丝  快来
Seelix. Front and center.
飞行训练课在20分钟以前就开始了
Flight instruction began 20 minutes ago, Seelix.
你想不想当驾驶员了?
You want to be a pilot or not?
想  长官  可我以为…
Yes, sir, but I thought that...
我让你以为的时候你再以为  傻蛋
You will think when I tell you to think, nugget.
你该看一下"全天计划"
And you might want to look at the plan of the day.
这样你就知道该去哪里
Because then, maybe you'll know where you're supposed to be
也就能按时到达
and you might actually get there on time.
没有你的制服和军靴
And you're out of uniform, to boot.
不好意思  上尉 这事交给我吧
Oh, I'm sorry, Captain. I think I can handle that.
谢谢  轮机长  拿着
Thank you, Chief. Hold this.
要想驾驶蝮蛇机  你必须是军官
You have to be an officer to fly Vipers.
这你也知道
You know that.
卫士  敬礼
Detail. Hand-salute!
谢谢  轮机长  谢谢您
Thank you, Chief. Thank you.
祝贺你  少尉
Congratulations, Ensign.
好感人的场面 可你在20分钟之前
All right, this is all very touching, but you were supposed to be
就应该到达预备室
in Ready Room Four 20 minutes ago, Ensign,
也就是说  少尉 你第一天报到就落后了
which means that you are falling behind on your first day.
快去
So move it.
别看他  快去  快去
Don't look at him! Move it! Move it!
对她好点
Be nice.